A Guide to the Correspondence and subject files of the Virginia Dept. of the State Internal Auditor, 1981-1991
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Correspondence and subject files of the Virginia Dept. of the State Internal Auditor, 1981-1991
The Library of Virginia
34903, 34911
2.7 cu. ft (4 boxes)
Virginia Dept. of the State Internal Auditor
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Accession 34903 transferred by the Dept. of the State Internal Auditor on June 15, 1995.
Accession 34911 transferred by the Dept. of the State Internal Auditor on June 27, 1995.
Historical Information
In August, 1980, the Commonwealth established an organization, the Office of the State Internal Auditor which, with the assistance of state agency heads and collegial bodies, was to improve the professional nature of auditing in state agency internal auditing programs. The Office of the State Internal Auditor functioned as a program within the Department of Accounts until July 1, 1985, when it was established as a separate entity, the Department of the State Internal Auditor (DSIA), under the Secretary of Finance.
The program was established because there were significant shortcomings reported in the State's overall internal auditing program in studies conducted by the Department of Management Analysis and Systems Development in 1979 and the Department of Information Technology in 1985. The statutory mandate to DSIA was "... to provide for the development and maintenance of internal audit programs in state agencies in order to ensure that the Commonwealth's assets are subject to appropriate internal management controls." To carry out this mission, the Department establishes state policies, standards, and procedures, provides state-of-the-art technical information, and assists in the professional development of agency internal auditors by developing and conducting training programs on a regular basis.
The State's internal auditing program was comprised of the DSIA and 39 individual agency units in the Executive Branch of government. These 40 units serve 49 different Executive Branch agencies. In addition to the support provided to Executive Branch agencies, DSIA also provided assistance to one independent agency, the Department of Lottery, one unit in the Judicial Branch, the Supreme Court of Virginia, and the Virginia Credit Union. The potential coverage provided by the 40 Executive Branch programs, when measured in terms of appropriation amounts, equated to 95.2% of the Commonwealth's appropriations.
In 2012, the DSIA was consolidated under a newly established Office of the State Inspector General (OSIG) along with the offices of inspector general of the Departments of Behavioral Health and Developmental Services, Corrections, Juvenile Justice, and Transportation. OSIG investigates complaints alleging fraud, waste, abuse or corruption by an executive branch state agency, non-state agency or officers, employees or contractors of those agencies; administers the Fraud and Abuse Whistle Blower Reward Fund; oversees the State Fraud, Waste and Abuse Hotline; conducts performance audits of state agencies; provides training and coordination of standards for the state's interal audit functions; performs inspections and conducts reviews of Healthcare Compliance Unit facilities and programs; and reviews operations of the Virginia Tobacco Region Revitalization Commission.
Scope and Content
Correspondence and subject files, 1981-1991, includes correspondence, reports, directives and memorandums. A majority of these records relate to financial reviews, efficiency evaluations, and auditing programs conducted by the Virginia Dept. of the State Internal Auditor. Some records relate to department discussions and planning around statewide auditing topics.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in its original order.
Contents List
- Correspondence and subject files, 1981-1991.
  - Accession 34903 (1981-1991).
    - VCU correspondence, 1981-1989. (Box 1)
    - Dept. of Accounts, 1986-1987. (Box 1)
    - Dept. of Accounts, 1988. (Box 1)
    - Dept. of Accounts, 1988-1989. (Box 1)
    - Dept. of Accounts, 1990. (Box 1)
    - Dept. of Aviation annual financial statements, 1982. (Box 1)
    - Dept. of Corrections, 1981-1988. (Box 1)
    - Dept. of Information Technology, 1987-1990. (Box 1)
    - Virginia Port Authority notes to financial statements, 1982. (Box 1)
    - Dept. of Transportation financial supplement to the Virgihia Highway Commission 75th Annual Report, 1982. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (General), 1980-1988. (Box 2)
    - Governor's Committee on Efficiency (1 of 6), 1986-1988. (Box 2)
    - Governor's Committee on Efficiency (2 of 6), 1986-1988. (Box 2)
    - Governor's Committee on Efficiency (3 of 6), 1986-1988. (Box 2)
    - Governor's Committee on Efficiency (4 of 6), 1986-1988. (Box 2)
    - Governor's Committee on Efficiency (5 of 6), 1986-1988. (Box 2)
    - Governor's Committee on Efficiency (6 of 6), 1986-1988. (Box 2)
    - IIA Central Virginia Chapter Board of Governors, 1986-1988. (Box 2)
    - Annual Audit Directors' meeting, 1988. (Box 2)
    - Annual Audit Directors' Meeting (1 of 2), 1989. (Box 2)
    - Annual Audit Directors' Meeting (2 of 2), 1989. (Box 2)
    - Annual Audit Directors' Meeting, 1990. (Box 2)
    - Annual Audit Directors' Meeting, 1991. (Box 2)
  - Accession 34911 (1981-1991).
    - Quality Assurance Committee, 1990. (Box 1)
    - John Huston memorandums and correspondence, 1990. (Box 1)
    - Southern Regional Conference correspondence, 1990-1991. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and memorandums, 1984-1989. (Box 1)
    - Correspondence: Internal Audit Directors (1 of 3), circa 1982-1990. (Box 2)
    - Correspondence: Internal Audit Directors (2 of 3), circa 1982-1990. (Box 2)
    - Correspondence: Internal Audit Directors (3 of 3), circa 1982-1990. (Box 2)
    - Personnel file: John Huston, circa 1981-1987. (Box 2)
    - Personnel file: John Huston audit report writing, circa 1983. (Box 2)
    - Personnel file: Phyllis C. Petree, circa 1987-1991. (Box 2)
    - Personnel file: Barrow, James R., circa 1987-1990. (Box 2)